<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Alberto Raimondi</title>
    <link>/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©Alberto Raimondi 2019-2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 20:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu6c3e0460bdc8551315ee635791325bb4_32749_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence: Decoding the Future</title>
      <link>/projects/ai_presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/ai_presentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had the opportunity to give a talk about Artificial Intelligence at an event specifically organized by the local Lions Club. During this unique occasion, I engaged with the audience about the transformative potential of AI, discussing how this cutting-edge technology is shaping our future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the event, I shared my experience as a Machine Learning Engineer, exploring the various ways in which AI is already being integrated into our daily lives and how it can drive innovation and progress. Interactions with guests revealed a growing enthusiasm for the possibilities offered by AI, along with a collective desire to navigate this new horizon with wisdom and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stimulating dialogue not only reaffirmed my passion for the field of AI but also underscored the importance of sharing knowledge and visions to collectively build a future that maximizes the potential of new technologies. Gatherings like this are essential for illuminating the path towards a technological adventure that promises excitement and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>U-WeAr: User Recognition  on  Wearable  Devices  through  Arm  Gesture</title>
      <link>/projects/uwear/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 14:13:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/uwear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Bianco Simone, Napoletano Paolo, Raimondi Alberto, Rima Mirko
&lt;strong&gt;Published in&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/9774362&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IEEE Transactions on Human-Machine Systems&lt;/a&gt; ( Volume: 52, Issue: 4, August 2022)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we present a hardware/software system for arm gesture recognition, identity recognition, and verification of a person based on inertial sensors. The hardware part is a custom wristband that consists of a computing unit, a wireless communication unit, and an inertial sensor. The software part is an algorithm based on recurrent neural networks that is able to process the signals coming from the sensor and to return a prediction.
To validate the system, a dataset consisting of 25 symbols drawn with the arm is collected.
These symbols are performed by 33 subjects. We conduct two evaluations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;performance evaluation for arm gesture recognition, user recognition and verification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;usability assessment of the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of the three recognition tasks indicate that this system can be reliably applied in real environments with an accuracy above 96% for gesture recognition, an accuracy of about 85% for user identification, and an equal error rate of about 13% for user verification. The outcome of the usability test proves a great satisfaction from the users in terms of high simplicity in the use of the wristband and goodness of the machine learning predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>U-Net for Medical Image Segmentation</title>
      <link>/projects/unet_for_medical_segmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/unet_for_medical_segmentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project, I helped researchers of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.unimi.it/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Università Degli Studi di Milano Statale&lt;/a&gt; to implement a fully automatic image segmentation model working with 2D, 3D, and 4D data.&lt;br /&gt;
The implemented model was a U-net architecture for medical image segmentation based on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MIC-DKFZ/nnUNet&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;nnUNet&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;br /&gt;
The results of this project are being used to research the possibility of automating craniofacial MRI and CT scans to improve the speed with which doctors can access meaningful patient analysis results.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-1-an-example-of-the-resulting-segmentation-of-a-human-abdomen&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 1: An example of the resulting segmentation of a human abdomen.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /projects/unet_for_medical_segmentation/2021-11-22_18-20-42_segmentation_hub996f2047cb67abdf4359bd5751c4072_152353_121dd5e3150a660558e4b39902a6ccb8.webp 400w,
               /projects/unet_for_medical_segmentation/2021-11-22_18-20-42_segmentation_hub996f2047cb67abdf4359bd5751c4072_152353_479442b47a46644be4adfcdcaaad673d.webp 760w,
               /projects/unet_for_medical_segmentation/2021-11-22_18-20-42_segmentation_hub996f2047cb67abdf4359bd5751c4072_152353_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/projects/unet_for_medical_segmentation/2021-11-22_18-20-42_segmentation_hub996f2047cb67abdf4359bd5751c4072_152353_121dd5e3150a660558e4b39902a6ccb8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;546&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;span class=&#34;figure-number&#34;&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;An example of the resulting segmentation of a human abdomen.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AESA adaptive beamforming using Deep Learning.</title>
      <link>/projects/aesabeamforming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 15:54:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/aesabeamforming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Bianco Simone, Feo Maurizio, Napoletano Paolo, Petraglia Giovanni, Raimondi Alberto, Vinetti Pietro.
&lt;strong&gt;Published in&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/conhome/9266310/proceeding&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2020 IEEE Radar Conference (RadarConf20)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this research paper, we explored the possibility of implementing state-of-the-art deep learning techniques to perform fast one-pass beamforming of electromagnetic signals to speed up interference counter-measures in adversarial scenarios.
We encode the signal into a 2D image to allow the use of computationally efficient convolutional neural networks to solve the beamforming task in a single pass of the network, skipping the slower iterative optimization approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Come si “costruisce” l’artista musicale di successo? Chiedilo a Spotify</title>
      <link>/projects/spotiwhy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/spotiwhy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this article published on the infodata section of the the IlSole24Ore website we conducted a brief descriptive  analysis of the key features of spotify hit songs of the year.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.infodata.ilsole24ore.com/2018/06/28/si-costruisce-lartista-musicale-successo-chiedilo-spotify/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Come si &amp;ldquo;costruisce&amp;rdquo; l&amp;rsquo;artista musicale di successo? Chiedilo a Spotify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​A. Raimondi, D. Meloni, S. Santamaria - 2018&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
